A Finding Aid to the Rescue Public Murals Records, 2001-2013, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Rescue Public Murals records
2001-2013
Archives of American Art
Heritage Preservation (Organization)
AAA.heripres
Archival Resource Key
1.2 Linear feet
10.68 Gigabytes
The records of Heritage Preservation's Rescue Public Murals program measure 1.2 linear feet and 10.68 GB and date from 2001 to 2013. The collection documents the assessment, restoration, and advocacy of several public outdoor murals throughout the country. Included are administrative records and project files containing email correspondence, project forms, press materials, photographs, technical specifications, and electronic records.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection was donated in 2015 by Heritage Preservation via Tom Clareson, former president.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2015 by Heritage Preservation via Tom Clareson, former president.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 2001-2013 (0.4 Linear feet; Box 1, 0.141 GB; ER01)
Series 2: Project Files, 2006-2012 (0.8 Linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 10.54 GB; ER02-ER14)
Biographical / Historical
Heritage Preservation (established 1982-2015) was an organization in Washington, D.C. working to preserve the nation's heritage for future generations through innovative leadership, education, and programs. In 2006, Heritage Preservation launched Rescue Public Murals, a program established to bring public attention to U.S. Murals, document their unique artistic and historic contributions, and secure the expertise and support to save them. Projects included mural assessments, restoration, creating written best practices for mural creation, advocacy, and documentation via digital photography. Heritage Preservation was established under the name National Institute for the Conservation of Cultural Property.
Scope and Contents
The records of Heritage Preservation's Rescue Public Murals program measure 1.2 linear feet and 10.68 GB and date from 2001 to 2013. The collection documents the assessment, restoration, and advocacy of several public outdoor murals throughout the country. Included are administrative records and project files containing email correspondence, project forms, press materials, photographs, technical specifications, and electronic records.
Photographs; Mural painting and decoration -- Conservation and restoration; Public art
- Administrative Records, 2001-2013; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1; 0.141 Gigabytes ER01
  Scope and Contents
  Administrative records include a few newspaper and magazine articles about the Rescue Public Murals program, forms used in mural assessments, and a brief institutional history. Also found are research notes, emails, and compiled resources regarding community murals, maintenance of public murals, and technical specifications for paints and other materials. General files include scattered meeting minutes and notes, email correspondence between program administrator Kristen Laise and others, drafts of program documents, and digital presentations.
  - Articles about Rescue Public Murals, 2006-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Community Mural Resources, 2003-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Forms, circa 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Files, 2006-2012; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01. (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - General Files, Digital Presentations and Documents, 2007-2008; Archival Resource Key; 0.141 Gigabytes Three computer files (Folder ER01)
  - Institutional History, circa 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Maintenance, 2001-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - National Conference on Mural Art, circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Technical Recommendations, 2003-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Project Files, 2006-2012; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2; 10.54 Gigabytes ER02-ER14
  Project files were maintained in two groups, by region and by mural project title. Files detail specific mural assessments, restoration work, project advocacy, and photographic documentation, and include forms, budgets, email correspondence, press materials, summaries, photographic prints, and records and photographs in digital format. Also found are unsorted photograph prints, slides, and digital photographs of various mural projects. Of note are extensive records detailing Rescue Public Mural's first restoration project in 2006 of "Homage to Seurat: La Grande Jatte in Harlem."
  - By Region, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Chicago, 2007-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - El Paso, 2006-2010; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER02. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - El Paso, Digital Photographs and Document, 2007-2008; Archival Resource Key; 0.581 Gigabytes 27 computer files (Folder ER02)
    - New Mexico, 2008-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Philadelphia, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - San Diego, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - San Francisco/Bay Area, 2008-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - By Title, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Centro Cultural de la Raza Murals, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER03. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Centro Cultural de la Raza Murals, Digital Photographs, 2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.151 Gigabytes 74 computer files (Folder ER03)
    - Common Threads, 2008-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Crossroads, 2008-2010; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER04. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Crossroads, Digital Photographs and Document, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.04 Gigabytes 40 computer files (Folder ER04)
    - Estrada Courts Murals, 2007-2008; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER05. (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Estrada Courts, Digital Photographs and Documents, 2007, 2010; Archival Resource Key; 2.54 Gigabytes 396 computer files (Folder ER05)
    - Homage to Seurat: La Grande Jatte in Harlem, 2007-2012; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER06-ER08. (Box 1, Folder 23-28)
    - Homage to Seurat: La Grande Jatte in Harlem, slideshow video by Jimena Rojas and Kristen Overbeck Laise, 2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.613 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER06)
    - Assessment and Preservation Project, Digital Photographs, Documents and Digital Video Recording, 2007-2010; Archival Resource Key; 4 Gigabytes 1032 computer files (Folder ER07)
    - Images of the African Diaspora in New York City Community Murals, exhibition at the Stony Brook University, NY, November 2 - December 18, 2009, Digital Photographs, Archival Resource Key; 0.032 Gigabytes 22 computer files (Folder ER08)
    - Multi-Cultural Progression, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER09. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Multi-Cultural Progression, Digital Photographs and Documents, 2008, Archival Resource Key; 0.811 Gigabytes 40 computer files (Folder ER09)
    - Our History Moves From Slavery Toward Freedom, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER10. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Our History Moves from Slavery Toward Freedom, Digital Photographs, 2008; Archival Resource Key; 0.195 Gigabytes 114 computer files (Folder ER10)
    - Seminole Peace Mural, 2008-2011; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER11. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Seminole Peace Mural, Digital Photographs, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.38 Gigabytes 50 computer files (Folder ER11)
    - SIDA en Colores (AIDS in Color), 2007-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Song of Unity Mural, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER12. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Song of Unity Mural, Digital Photographs and Document, 2008; Archival Resource Key; 0.309 Gigabytes 214 computer files (Folder ER12)
    - Under City Stone, 2007-2008; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER13. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Under City Stone, Digital Photographs and Digital Video Recordings, 2008; Archival Resource Key; 0.217 Gigabytes 113 computer files (Folder ER13)
  - Project Photographs and Slides, Miscellaneous, 2004-2007; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER14. (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Project Photographs, Digital Photographs, 2007, 2010; Archival Resource Key; 0.666 Gigabytes 447 computer files (Folder ER14)